# **Dave Lotito**

## Data Scientist, Assistant Vice President

Professional data scientist at Citizens Financial Group with more than 2 years of experience analyzing large data sets and developing data driven decisions for fortune 500 companies. Involved in various projects where I have led multiple teams to success. Primarily worked in teams of 4-12.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Data Scientist, Advanced Analytics**

June 2020 - Present

Citizens, Providence, RI

- Spearheaded the creation of the banks first OCR (Optical Character Recognition) machine learning software for the acquisition and transition of HSBC consumer banking customers. Software successfully extracted, predicted, and identified letters & digits in FDIC Trust and FDIC Signature Card documents with near perfect accuracy. Software saved the organization ~\$500k & reduced manual intervention.
- Leveraged AWS Textract low-level client for detecting and analyzing text in documents to convert the text into machine-readable output for Citizens FDIC joint signature card document extraction for millions of documents.
- Managed the banks' consumer collections models, helping implement the various model control points needed to mitigate risk and catch issues.
- Created a data validation pipeline in Amazon SageMaker using Python to streamline the EDA process & check for data anomalies ensuring our data is clean and ready for modeling.
- Created, improved, and maintained the LIBOR Sourcing python-based applications. Each day review Jira for user stories based on business needs and new requirements.
- Developed the missing documents python-based application to account for documents that weren't found in our sourcing code but were in-scope documents that the business team would need to manually retrieve. The script successfully accounted for thousands of missing documents that were needed for the LIBOR transition initiative.
- Lead the Document Analytics tasks as the SME for our team.
  Successfully tagged and categorized the newly ingested documents for each quarterly refresh to streamline the search process for downstream stakeholders.

## **Business Strategy & Operations**

May 2019 - August 2019

Fidelity Investments · Internship, Merrimack, NH

- Functioned within an Agile team on various projects where I completed complex business analysis problems to solve issues within PI / CCP to better service our customers.
- Aggregated data to calculate which Fidelity branches have the largest number of financial advisor & relationship manager associates for the WIN10 / Outlook migration strategy.
- Performed analysis leveraging SQL on inbound and outbound emails to help solve routing problems with associate communication between clients.

#### CONTACT

- Providence, RI (Open to Remote)
- 978-973-4253
- DavidJLotito@gmail.com
- www.linkedin.com/in/david-lotito
- · github.com/davelotito

#### **SKILLS**

#### Data Visualization/Engineering:

- Tableau
- Sisense
- Plotly
- Matplotlib

#### Techniques:

- Hypothesis Testing
- Classification
- Linear Regression
- Anomaly Detection
- Neural Networks
- Resampling Methods

#### Tools and Frameworks:

- AWS (SageMaker, Athena, S3)
- Python (Numpy, Pandas, Keras, Tensorflow, Matplotlib, Seaborn)
- R (ggplot, dplyr, tidyr, plotly, knitr)
- Databases (MySQL)
- Excel

## **EDUCATION**

#### **Boston University**

MSc, Applied Data Analytics Boston, MA — September 2021 -Present

## University of Massachusetts, Lowell

BSc, Management Information Systems & Marketing Analytics Lowell, MA — September 2016 – May 2020

## **CERTIFICATES**

- Python for Data Science & Machine Learning
- Tableau Data Analytics & Visualization
- Advanced Deep Learning with Keras & Image Processing